aws...

Review all…

Video game engines

1. GameMaker Studio 2
2. Unity
3. Unreal 

——————
Meeting ID: 988 4973 7945
Passcode: vy6fGs

First day
——————————
V8 is written in c++ and it runs javascript.

Angular is a UI framework
Expressjs is framework for web

Node is single threaded but performs more than multithreaded ones

Data driven application is what we will be learning different from data driven design

Expresss runs on top of node and pretty much everything runs on top of node.

-blocking and Non blocking code and is resolved through child process

Express application is a node that uses express. And u van use it using require express
——————
Second day
————

~x.y.z means not including x.y+1.0

Connecting from getting method(routing) and controller and vice verbal is called middleware.

Middleware runs in order

When adding routers the specific ones at the top and the generic ones at the bottom
————————
Day3

We can also use Mysql for this application but its usually for mobile applications so we don’t need as heavy as MySql

-theres no schema in noSql so that’s what the benefit is.

-key value is mostly used 

-in Mysql, there are two cases DDL DML but in noSql we have four and we will be working with document store mongoDB

—sql is proven mathematically that it won’t make mistakes but not in noSql.
— sql are designed for enterprise applications
—callback makes asynchronous calls which is good.
— mangoose enforces schema
—we don’t install mango globally
—creating a database connection is expensive that’s why we don’t do it in every controller.

—we only open the connection once in out application and then we simply use a get method to get the connection.

—the data base doesn’t enforce error checking because it doesn’t have any schema. So we enforce it using errors.


Steps
1.Nom install mongodb
2.import data ; mongo restore —db meanGames —gzip dump/meanGames
———————
Day 05

-headless application means backend application
—manogoose runs on top of the driver mongodb
—schema is json
- buffer is where u store binary data like images. 
Single schema is for single document not whole collectio

—the callback is sending the message not the thread.



============
Weekend project
=============
Get one movie
GET /api/movies/:movieId
Update movie
PUT /api/movies/:movieId
Delete movie
DELETE /api/movies/:movieId
Get all movies
GET /api/movies
Add movie
POST /api/movies
———————————————

ANGULAR
——————

Angular is running on the client side but exresss and nodejs are on server side

—once you add routes then its no more single page application.  That’s why we use servers like python3

———————
Week three= angular 
———————————
-One thing about prototypes is having static pages.

-Full stack is basically developing the whole application from end to end.

Front end is the UI and back end is the database or the servers but Middle is your business logic or applications logic.

-Node: is a JS platform, its the foundation of the mean stack. This is because express runs on top of node, we can still design a web server using node but using express is way easier.

-so node is fast and efficient and scalable when coded correctly means when is it non blocking. Its light on system save resources because it is running on single threaded.

-npm is node package manager.

—prototype : we will be using a data driven application 
We develop an api using node and express, 

First step: We start a prototype with the UI because its just a show model. 

Second step: we create the mongoDBD
Third step: we create the api’s

We talked about semVer when we talked about npm.
—express 
Mvc is not a algorithm its a pattern.
-the architect we had last week was: a rest api feeding angular UI other architecture is hybrid architecture

-so we have hybrid mean architecture which helps for browsers engines to search the static pages.

———————————
nodeJS is server side JS platform 
V8 is c++ that understands JS,  converts JS to machine, its written by Google. Introduced with chrome web browser to enable JS.

- it uses libuv , libuv is something that lets us run node as asynchronous I/o. And its used by Microsoft,google and uber

Chrome runs on cross platform, can run in every OS so then since nodjs runs on top of v8 chrome then nodejs runs on every OS.

Event driven means an event triggered by the client with mouse or buttons on event click.

ECMA script - standardizing java script.
Every browser has its own javascript compiler.

I/O operations in ddd is expensive because it eats up lots of resources.

-parallel: codes running simultaneously, at exactly same time
-concurrency: one after the other, but it give illusion of parallel . Concurrency started on 95
-parrallelism: run one task at a time, only run next task after first task is done.
-Async: being able to start a task and then continue execution before side task finishes(gives illusion of concurrency)

Nodejs.server — to be googled later

REPL- Read Evaluate Print Loop- in command line it REPLs like when we do node in cmd and we are in its loop environment

When ever we do node start: then there three happens;
     -Bootstrap : Load node and if JS code.. it loads the node code that needs to run
     - Main scope: Load and run user code 
     - Event Loop: starts after main scope(user code) exit, if async task has scheduled run them then run callbacks else exit.
These are all done by express.

Deep concept of node is that its single threaded and multi threaded at the same time

setinterval, clearInterval,setTimeOut and etc… are all used for setting timer in the event loop.

-Event loop is an entity that handles external events and converts that to callbacks. Loop that picks, events from the events queue and pushes them(callbacks) into call stack.
NB. When v8 is running hen event loop is not running.

There are several queues: Tiemer,pendingcallback,Idle, pool,chekc, close callbacks. We call tick when completing the 6 queus and returns back.
 

-Timers: setTimeout(f),setInterval
-Pending callbacks: least important callback on top connections
-idle: for internal node usage
-poll: most important queue: uses for I/o operations, uses for encryption and decryption(this is when used for callbacks)
This is where you have network req and res, where u have I/O response and where encryption happens.
This is where we put most of our callbacks.
-check- setImmediate  (fun), fun is inserted here: setImmediate is quicker than setTimeout because check is after poll.
-all queus share same limit
-when we do findOne and then exec-> the callback is put in poll section so what happens is since the timer is going to mongoldb and searching for the query twhen wwehne node reaches the node 

————
Nexttick : means stop on the tick where u are and proceed with the next Tick. Its priority queue.

Next tick has more priority than microtick(which is found in v8) and this one has priority over tick.

We can use nodeJs to do any general purpose applications

—————
How does chrome work?
When chrome starts UI, Network and Storage threads start 
UI job to decide what happens to view

Each tap. Have its own process: main reason is security
Each tab is isolated: v8 independent process

Render process render all the html,css,js and images and get it back to browsers.

CPU and GPU differences?

In http1 there only were 6 connection but I http2 unlimited.
With http2 everything is encrypted.

DOM(main thread) and style tree exist in chrome. The style tree gets its style from css.

The main thread combines DOM to style tree to create layout tree.

The  main thread using paint record converts the layers in to sets of instructions. And these are called paint records;
Then the roaster thread creates the pixels and send it to the GPU .

Then the GPU coordinates with the CPU and answers does this need to be displayed.
MANIPULATING the Dom is the job of angular or react framework.

-when browser needs a js in the file then the V8 is single threaded so it stops the processs to fetch the js.
Modifiying the Dom is expensive

Defer and async ? In javascript.

Angular js doesn’t support all the browser thing.


// exam highlights 

Fullstack
Node 
Browser
Coding
Interview questions from googling 2 to 3 question

————————————————————————
Friday
——————
201 successful post
204 successful delete(no content)
304 not modified (get request results not modified “no body”)
400 bad reg, unsuccessful get, post, put (invalid contents)
401 unauthorized, incorrect credentials, invalid token 
403 forbidden, request not allowed, customer doesn’t exist, application trying to access proper ting not belonging to the app
404 not found, incorrect parameter in URL, bad input parameters,
405 method not allowed , method not allowed for given URL , resource doesn’t support this method
409 conflict   unsuccessful post, post another object with same data exist
410 gone the the requested data is no longer available on the system.
500 internal server error , problem with server of db
503 service unavailable 

Replication:
-replica set is a set of one primary and several secondary nodes and optionally arbiter nodes.

Regular node (primary, secondary
Arbiter node(for voting purpose, if we have only two machines)
Delayed node(disaster node, as back up node, if everything falls down)
Hidden node(for analytics)

All nodes can participate in voting

If mongoldb driver can not send messages to the primary because it is busy and processing some stuffs then it buffers and has a buffer and puts every request that comes to the buffer. The driver has a buffer which is pretty cool.

Replication write concern:

W:0 returns success immediately. When the request comes to the driver it immediately says done even if it is in buffer.

W:1 return success only after successful write to primary. you care in your code wihich state u are at

W:2 return success after successful write to primary at least one secondary. Basically you at least have one back up secondary.
 

When a request comes, the mongoDB driver communiacates with  primary node and when primary node goes offline then the secondary nodes vote on becoming the primary.


Replica read preferences:
The driver Read from primary or secondary or nearest node

Seedlist : 30010, 30020 etc are local hosts that are called seed list.

If we give one local host then we are working with one node like we worked on recent applications like meanGames.

The rules of replication:
Seed list: at least one other node exists beside the primary
You have to have Write concerns: 
You have to have Read preferences:
You have to have Error handling

sharding(pieces);
Dividing into different hard drives.

Shard A and shard B share the huge/big collection into two of them.

This is becas when your data is so huge. So there is vertical and horizontal scaling.
Vertical scaling is by adding ram, hdd of cpu power on a single machine.

Horizontal scaling is just add a new server of machine.

The advantage of sharding is performance. By putting in different collections then it becomes fast when fetching the list of items . For best performance put the video 50/50  into two sharing balancing the data otherwise if they are not propotional then that is the disadvantage.

To overcome this problem then we have hashing function:
When you have items in array of that size, ehtn sorting the takes a lot of time. What hashing will do is that it will put 100 space but store 500 by hashing them. Hashing is as powerful as making your array even.

Shard key is an index in each document to help identify the shard where this doc is stored.

Adding and removing shadring:  

When adding shards to a cluster then we need to balance and take some of the shards to it.

To remove a shard, move out the data to other shards and remove the shard.




——
We may have to update the create method to enable it to function properly after deletes. Update the controller in api/routes/publisher-controller.js Module.exports.publisherAdd= function(req, res) { … if(game) { if(!(game.publisher)) { game.publisher= {name: "empty", location: []}; } _ad

———————
07rjvb9e

